<?xml version="1.0"?>
<book xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation='http://www.docbook.org/xsd/4.4/docbook.xsd' >
<!-- :wrap=soft:maxLineLen=0: -->
<title>jEdit CtagsInterface Plugin Guide</title>
<bookinfo>
 <authorgroup>
  <author><firstname>Shlomy</firstname><surname>Reinstein</surname></author>
 </authorgroup>

 <legalnotice><title>Legal Notice</title>
  <para>
   Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
   under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
   any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
   <quote>Invariant Sections</quote>, <quote>Front-Cover Texts</quote> or
   <quote>Back-Cover Texts</quote>, each as defined in the license. A copy of
   the license can be found in the file <filename>COPYING.DOC.txt</filename>
   included with jEdit.
  </para>

 </legalnotice>
 </bookinfo>

 <chapter id="intro">
  <title> Introduction </title>

 <para>
  The CtagsInterfacePlugin provides three dockables, a
  <guilabel>Tag List</guilabel>, a <guilabel>Tag Preview</guilabel> and a
  <guilabel>Progress</guilabel>. It also provides a number of operations that
  allow you to quickly jump from one file location to another in the editor,
  based on the context of the caret, and the indexed tag information obtained
  from the <ulink url="http://ctags.sourceforge.net/">Exuberant Ctags</ulink>
  executable. And finally, it provides a plugin interface through which other
  jEdit plugins can easily access ctags data.
 </para>
 </chapter>

 <chapter id="setup">
 <title> Setup and Configuration </title>

 <para>
  CtagsInterface will happily index all files in your project or source
  tree, unless you tell it otherwise.
  Under <literal>Plugin Options - CtagsInterface - General</literal> you will
  find a field for specifying
  <emphasis role="bold">Ctags Invocation Options</emphasis>. By adding extra
  options to this field, as shown below, you can specify that only certain
  file types are scanned and indexed. Read the manual pages of exuberant ctags
  for more information about the options available.
 </para>

 <literallayout> --languages=c,c++,java,python </literallayout>
 
</chapter>
 <chapter id="tagdbs">
   <title> Tagging Projects, Source Trees/Archives and Tag/Source Files</title>

   <para>
    CtagsInterface uses a Lucene index to keep track of tag data from multiple
    projects, directory trees/archives and tag/source files. The
    <guimenuitem>Plugin Options - CtagsInterface</guimenuitem> provides
    dialogs for adding projects, directory trees/archives and tag/source files 
	that should be indexed.
   </para>

   <para>
    The first step is to add the projects, source trees/archives or tag/source files
	 that you want to be tagged in the index. Tagging is done in the background, you 
	 can continue working with jEdit meanwhile. The tagging progress is shown in the
    <guilabel>Progress</guilabel> dockable, in a tab of a tabbed pane. When
    done, you can lookup tags from the projects, source trees/archives and tag/source files.
   </para>

   <para>
    You can add projects two ways. From the ProjectViewer, right click on the
    project and <guimenuitem>Add Project to index</guimenuitem>, or from
    <guimenuitem>Plugin Options - CtagsInterface - Projects</guimenuitem>.
   </para>

   <para>
    Similarly, you can add source trees/archives from
    <guimenuitem>Plugin options - CtagsInterface - Source Trees</guimenuitem>. 
    You can also add source trees from the file system browser context menu:
    <guimenuitem>Plugins - Add source tree to tag index</guimenuitem>.
	
	Lastly tag and source files can be added from
    <guimenuitem>Plugin options - CtagsInterface - Files</guimenuitem>
	and the source file currently in your buffer can be added through 
	the <guimenuitem>Add current file</guimenuitem> action.
   </para>

   <para>
	Tags can be removed from the index using the options pane, actions in 
	<guimenuitem>Plugins - CtagsInterface</guimenuitem> or the ProjectViewer 
	context menu
   </para>
   
 </chapter>

 <chapter id="lookup">
   <title> Tag Lookup </title>

   <para>
    By default, tag lookup will search the entire tag index for matching tags,
    including all added projects and source trees.
   </para>

   <para>
    When using jEdit with ProjectViewer, you might be working with a set of
    files, and have to frequently check another set of files that you are
    reusing. This means that you will probably want to restrict your search
    to only the projects and source trees that are related to your project.
   </para>

   <para>
    By editing the properties of the current project, you can see a
    <guilabel>Dependencies</guilabel> pane, which allows you to set the
    related projects, source trees/archives or tag files on an individual project basis. While
    running the Tag Preview, or performing a Jump to Tag while working in a
    project that has dependencies set, CtagsInterface should restrict its
    searches to tag data from only those projects and directory trees.
   </para>

   <para>
    This is especially useful in the case where there are many projects /
    source trees indexed in the tags database that are not related to each
    other.
   </para>
   
	<para>
	In addition, when the option to 'Match tags with language of current buffer' is selected 
	tooltips and completion suggestions will only be shown from tags whose language 
	matches that of the file in the current buffer, which can be useful when working with
	multiple languages. File extension is used to do this matching and the mapping can be 
	seen by calling ctags with the <literal>--list-maps</literal> option. If the source 
	file's language hasn't been tagged nothing will be shown, to fix this retag your 
	source files including the 'l' flag in the ctags <literal>--fields</literal> option.
	</para>

 </chapter>

 <chapter id="actions">
   <title> Actions </title>

   <formalpara><title> Add tag File </title>
   <para>
    Adds an already generated ctags file to the database.
   </para>
   </formalpara>

   <formalpara><title> Tag all projects </title>
   <para>
    This does exactly what it says: it goes through
    <emphasis role="bold">every</emphasis> project that ProjectViewer knows
    about, and tags their files, adding the tag data to the embedded database.
   </para>
   </formalpara>

   <formalpara><title> Suggest completion options </title>
   <para>
    Suggests code-completion options from the tag database. This includes
    completion of function calls, using SuperAbbrevs for conveniently
    filling-in the parameter values.
   </para>
   </formalpara>

   <section id="dynamic-actions">
   <title> Dynamic Actions </title>

   <para>
    In addition to these built-in actions, CtagsInterface allows you to create
    dynamic Actions, which are custom Lucene queries, which can be bound to
    keyboard shortcuts. Each such Lucene query should retrieve a list of tags
    from the database. There are 3 types of dynamic actions:
    <orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>
     Jump to tag - execute the query and show the list of tags it retrieved
     in the <guilabel>Tag List</guilabel> dockable, allowing you to jump to any
     of them. In case the query returns a single tag, the dynamic action jumps
     to it directly, without showing it in the dockable.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Search prefix - execute the query and show the "Prefix search" popup so
     you can choose a tag from the query results using its prefix. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem> <para>
     Search string - execute the query and show the "Prefix search" popup so
     you can choose a tag from the query results using a substring. </para>
    </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   </para>
   <para>
    To manage (create/delete/modify) dynamic actions, select the
    <guilabel>Actions</guilabel> pane in the plugin options. To define a new
    dynamic action, click the <guilabel>+</guilabel> button. You will be asked
    to provide a name for the action and a Lucene query. The action name you
    provide should not contain spaces, as it is used to define an ordinary
    edit action. The Lucene query can make use of the following keywords:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guilabel>{tag}</guilabel>: The tag being looked up
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guilabel>{project}</guilabel>: The name of the active project
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   Here are a few examples:
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>_name:{tag} AND kind:function AND origin:{project}
	  </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>_name:{tag} AND kind:prototype AND origin:{project}
	  </para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   </para>

   </section>

 </chapter>

 <chapter id="dockables">
   <title> CtagsInterface Dockables </title>

   <para>
    There are three dockables that you can use from CtagsInterface. 
   </para>

   <formalpara> <title> Tag List </title>
   <para>
    When <action>jump to tag</action> is invoked, if there is more than one
    possible match, the Tag List dockable is displayed, where you can preview
    and select the choices of jump locations.
   </para>

   </formalpara>
   <formalpara> <title> Tag Preview </title>
   <para>
    This dockable is updated automatically (after a configurable delay)
    whenever the caret is moved over a location that is a known symbol in the
    tag index.
   </para>

   </formalpara>
   <formalpara> <title> Progress </title>
   <para>
    This dockable shows the progress of tagging activities in a tabbed pane.
    Each activity has its own tab. By default, a tab closes automatically a
    few seconds after the activity is over, but you can configure this in the
    <guilabel>General </guilabel> option pane.
    You can close a tab manually by middle-clicking the tab title or clicking
    the <guilabel>Close</guilabel> button in the dockable.
   </para>

   </formalpara>

 </chapter>

 <chapter id="pluginservices">
   <title> Services to other plugins </title>
   <para>
    CtagsInterface also offers services to other plugins, such as ClassBrowser
    and CodeHelper:
   </para>

   <orderedlist>
   <listitem><para> Queries of the tag index</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para> Jumping to tags </para></listitem>
   </orderedlist>

   <para>
    Since the CtagsInterface manages the tag information and runs ctags, other
    plugins do not need to call/depend on ctags directly. This also means that
    in the future, the CtagsInterface may be extended to work with other
    code-indexing tools.
   </para>

  </chapter>

<appendix id="changelog">
 <title> Changelog </title>
  <para> For a list of changes in this plugin, see the
  <ulink url="docs/CHANGES.txt">change log</ulink>.
  </para>


</appendix>


</book>
